I'm also very happy to be here.
I very much feel at home.
Even driving through and coming here, getting closer to Lerab Ling, I feel a strong kind of happiness, joy, because this place very much holds the lineage of my Master and our lineage Masters.
somehow feels like coming to a kind of holy you know it is holy but very strong strong feeling that coming to a very holy kind of place and written with lots of memories so I'm very happy to be here and very happy to see all of you radiating radiating
So today, first teaching was the Shinye, Shinye practice by Chabjithi Muchenzi Rinpoche's commentary on Jango-Mepham Rinpoche's Buddha Shakyamuni practice.
So, as you know, in Tibet, not so much emphasis on starting practice with shinai.
But many of my friends who are now teaching in the West, they say that shinai is very, very important.
They feel it's very important.
Because now we live in a kind of world where everything is so busy and so much disturbing to our mind.
So our mind is completely like boiling water.
due to the situation and circumstances but in tibet everything is so calm it's naturally kind of shinny by just by being there karma binding kind of environment so maybe it was not emphasized so much in tibet that time i went to mount kailash once a few years ago
So after you come out of the car, then you have to walk towards the circumambulation.
It was so quiet.
There's no sound at all.
Almost like what Japanese say, sound of the silent.
So silent.
So I thought, well, this kind of place, environment is perfect for meditating and practice dharma because there's no disturbance at all.
So quiet.
So Tibet is a little bit like that.
So therefore, maybe that's why not so much emphasis on shinny practice.
So then the second, first day was so inspired.
It took me three days to go around.
First day was so inspired and I was like, this is the place if you want to do practice.
Then second day I was so tired.
So the inspiration is gone.
When I climb over the mountain, it's almost 6,000 meters.
So I was not this big, I was a little bit big at that time.
So I had to hold the yak's tail to pull me up.
So like that.
So in Tibet, I think very calm, naturally calm, so maybe not so much important.
But I think nowadays in this kind of very busy world and our mind is so much disturbed.
So I think to do any kind of practice, like development practice or whatever, I think it's very important to start with shinye, calm, abiding mind.
So I think it's very good that I can give a little bit kind of explanation and then you have the books to carry on with further study.
.
When I was young, I used to go to the temple to pray.
I used to go to the temple to pray.
And so to begin the teaching on calm abiding, reading from Khyentse Rinpoche's text, The Sage Who Dispels Mind's Anguish, advice from the guru, the gentle protector, Manjushri, on the means of accomplishing the yogas of Samatha and Vipassana, homage to the guru, Shakyamuni.
When training in the yogas of Samatha, calm abiding, and Vipassana, insight,
By focusing on the body of the teacher, Buddha, infuse your mind with precious bodhicitta, the wish to attain Buddhahood for the benefit of all sentient beings.
Generally, when we practice calm abiding meditation,
we need an object upon which to sustain our attention.
And I think generally speaking it's okay to use any object, any ordinary object such as a flower or whatever, stone or pebble or what have you.
However, there are extraordinary reasons and benefits for meditating upon the extraordinary object that is the form of the Buddha.
.
Now there's an important line here.
It says, infuse your mind with the precious bodhicitta, the wish to attain Buddhahood for the benefit of all sentient beings.
As practitioners of the Mahayana, the greater vehicle,
It is imperative when beginning any activity to initially give rise to the mind that aspires to awaken for the benefit of all sentient beings or bodhicitta.
Accordingly one should reflect upon the vastness of space and how existing there within are countless individuals in the state of dissatisfaction or suffering and wishing to free them from that state.
Accordingly, with this vast motivation of bodhicitta, that is to say being held with or from within that attitude, whatever activity that we engage will bring about extraordinary kind of merit, benefit and wonderment.
.
These days.
we find ourselves continually in a state of busyness, don't we?
And accordingly, when we're in a rush to do our daily kind of practices, the idea of cultivating or framing the motivation of bodhicitta within which to engage our future practices just simply gets forgotten.
And then when it comes to the actual practices themselves, they are kind of rushed, rushed through.
And so I feel it is imperative that we give the proper attention to the framing of our motivation.
Giving rise to this extraordinary attitude of bodhicitta will make whatever practice we do
whether it be calm abiding meditation whether we are doing a particular ritual connected with a sadhana or whatever whatever activity we do when it is held by bodhicitta it becomes meritorious it becomes the dharma if you like these days around the world the idea of mindfulness what we might call secular mindfulness is extremely popular
But that is a worldly activity, if you like.
And whilst it might be quite useful, it is of the world.
And as a result thereof, one will accomplish something that is of the world, what we might call then the absorptions of the form of the formless realms.
However, if we were to engage the practice of calm abiding meditation within the attitude of bodhicitta, then that would become the path of the Dharma.
And its result will be similarly in accord with its cause, bodhicitta.
.
As was made clear during the announcement, here we find ourselves gathered in a group that is comprised of many people from various backgrounds, from many places, countries, different countries around the world.
And we've all invested, of course, our time, but financially, we've invested in the airfare, the taxi fare, the train fare, whatever.
And so perhaps some of you at the beginning reflected, there is some Dharma activity at Lerabling.
I'm going to go there so as to receive the teaching, to practice it, so as to awaken for the benefit of all sentient beings.
And with that motivation, you booked your flight, arranged the train fare, taxis, and what have you.
I'm sure some of you did that.
Others, maybe not.
I don't know.
However, when we reflect upon holding our activities or framing our motivation with bodhicitta, if we have that attitude at the very beginning, then every step we take towards entering the temple at Lherabaling, every kilometer that we travel, every pound or euro, dollar, if you will, that we've spent on airfare, etc., becomes the dharma beneficial of the greater vehicle.
That's why I think it's very important to have a good relationship with the Buddha.
That's why I think it's important to have a good relationship with the Buddha.
I am very happy to be able to speak with you today.
And so I'd like to pretty much emphasize this point at the beginning, that whatever activity we would like to do, whether it be the practice of calm abiding, whatever, the framing of the motivation at the beginning is extremely important.
For this framing then kind of dictates what kind of color the activity that we are about to engage takes.
And so to give rise to this precious attitude is incredibly important.
If not, then meditation becomes something ordinary, you might say.
And so there are various kind of reasons or needs, etc., to frame our motivation, which I mentioned here.
However, when we reflect simply, we are individuals who are affected by the contaminant of confusion, and thereby we cycle in existence samsara.
Essentially, the reason we endure the perpetual difficulty of samsara is because we cannot control our mind.
Our mind is beyond control.
And so then, essentially, one needs to control the mind for the very reason of achieving liberation or separation from this perpetual state of dissatisfaction.
In the past, when I used to go to the temple, I used to go to the temple to pray.
I used to go to the temple to pray.
Previously, Khyentse Rinpoche gave a teaching on mind at Rigpa.
At that point, he mentioned the benefits of calm abiding for the very purpose of subduing or calming or taming, if you like, the unruly mind.
This is extremely important.
All the kind of key points of practice are included in that little teaching.
And so the teaching, I think, is called Mind Teaching by Dingo Khyentse Rinpoche.
It's a video.
I think it was given in Prabhupada.
So from that time, Patrick's voiceover.
So that is an extremely important video.
Every essential or quintessential point is in that short discourse, so I very much encourage you to watch that.
.
We read,
At the time when I've obtained the support of the freedoms and riches and met the Tathagata's teaching, I will put aside all worldly activities which only bring about negative results.
All those such practices as making offerings to the Tathagata's form and so on,
do generate immeasurable merit.
These accumulations of merit are based on material wealth, are something that the Tathagata advised mainly for householders.
And so here, this is a particular reference to Buddhist culture, you may say Himalayan culture in particular.
within which there is the custom of going to the temple to make offerings to the forms of the Buddha, offerings to the Sanghas and so forth.
But whilst this is in and of itself meritorious, it is not really going to help with the subjugation of the unruly or the taming of the unruly mind.
as something far superior for renunciates, those following in his own footsteps.
He prays discipline and genuine inward resting.
So here then this is reference to the fully awakened one, the Buddha.
For those then who follow in his footsteps, Sangha, if you will, he prays then the practice of morality or discipline as the foundation for genuine inward resting.
This then is in accordance with the Tathagata's words.
Therefore, reflecting upon them...
Why don't you take up the pledge, if you like, to practice them as much as you can.
If you want to know more, please subscribe to our channel and press the bell icon.
When we eat, we have a lot of food.
I was very happy to be able to do this.
In particular, throughout the course of beginningless time, we have been disturbed day and night, without break, by all kinds of conceptual thoughts, rather like the stirring of wind or clouds or waves on the ocean.
and we have been brought low.
Not only have we failed to accomplish a single remarkable quality, where we are afflicted by all manner of suffering.
Since that is so, reflect
I will now free myself, however I can, from the mire of these difficult, conflicting thoughts.
And even if, just for a single instant, focus on the Tathagata's body, which is of such great merit and significance.
In doing so, I shall achieve the yogas of calm abiding and insight in their proper way.
And so here, we're taught to reflect upon
the nature of discursive thought.
When we reflect genuinely, honestly upon them, what have they brought us?
What good have they brought us?
If we were to consider ourselves, if we were to consider our mind and the discursive thoughts running therein, let's say we were to give them form, they probably wouldn't fit in this temple, would they?
And so when we think about it, the sheer volume of discursive thought that we give to every day, okay, there's a lot of them.
But what benefit have they brought us?
There's great benefit to them.
Great.
But it's the opposite, isn't it?
All of these disturbing thoughts have only brought us dissatisfaction and further dissatisfaction.
Accordingly, we've been brought low as we read.
And this is simply through failing to tame the unruly mind.
Accordingly, it is imperative before engaging in the practice of sitting meditation to consider then the faults of perpetually remaining under the influence of discursive thought.
Thoughts then that have only brought us dissatisfaction and will only lead to further dissatisfaction.
.
If you want to know more about Samson Dramas, please visit our website at www.samson.org
And so we read, I will now free myself however I can from the mire of these conflicting thoughts.
And the way of doing that is to focus upon an object that will be then a support for our practice.
And as we read, even if to focus for a single instant on the body or the form of the Tathagata, Buddha, is of such great merit and significance
And so accordingly, using the support of the body or the form of the Buddha, reflect then that I will now engage in the practice of calm abiding and insight, establishing them or developing them in the proper way.
That's all.
For this, one is encouraged here to make an intense pledge of single-pointed or one-pointed yearning, reflecting, Guru, victorious ones and your descendants, I supplicate you, grant your blessing that I may succeed.
Here then, one requests the blessing and inspiration of the root and lineage masters, the Buddhas and Bodhisattvas, etc., such that one will succeed in the practice of the meditation to come.
If you want to know more, you can go to our website at www.youtube.com.tumblr.com.
And so initially, then, the place where one is to practice, we read, first of all, remove yourself from hustle and bustle.
And so here, in particular, one should give up the idea of trying to practice in a place that is full of disturbance.
We often hear about renunciates here.
One can be renouncing, then, distraction, external distraction arising from this hustle and bustle.
and we should go to a place without impediments to meditative concentration such as people moving about during the day or kind of a hubbub at night.
Here we're encouraged to sit comfortably and practice in an area that is completely free of external disturbances that come from a different kind of noisy individuals.
I am very happy to be able to share my knowledge with you all.
And so we're encouraged to sit in a comfortable posture for the meditation posture it says here.
So then what is a meditation posture?
F1 has the subtlety of body and length of bone.
Then we can sit in the full lotus posture, but if not, then we can simply sit in a comfortable seated posture, cross-legged or whatever, or failing that, we can sit in a chair.
It doesn't really matter.
What does matter is that you're comfortable.
.
And now we read a very important instruction.
Thoroughly mix your mind stream with the preliminary dharmas.
So here, this can refer to a number of contemplations.
For example, we can reflect upon the four thoughts that turn the mind to spiritual practice, reflecting on the preciousness of our human experience, its changing nature, the effects of previously engaged action, and the reflection on cause and effect in general.
But closer to home, for this particular meditation or activity that we are to do, we should reflect upon the reason that we need to subdue the unruly mind, the benefits of subduing said mind, etc.
Think about the demerits of continually being under the influence of this discursive thought again and again.
.
And then for the actual practice, one is encouraged to place in front of you, at whatever height and position is comfortable to you, a beautiful and pleasing image of the Tathagata Buddha, the King of the Shakyas.
And this image should be one that has been drawn correctly by a skilled artist.
And, with the power of aspiration, recall the Tathagata's blessings, and by reciting the essence of causation mantra, consecrate the image.
Having done this, place it at whatever distance is right for you to look at.
And this distance should be one that is not too close, nor should it be too far away.
It should be placed at a position that is just right for you.
Have a good day.
When I was young, I used to go to the temple to pray.
I used to go to the temple to pray.
When it comes to the image of the Buddha, we generally use a picture of the Bodhgaya image of the Buddha, the Bodhgaya statue.
And so if you look behind me, you'll see a wonderful representation of Buddha Shakyamuni.
So this is based on the Bodhgaya Buddha image.
And so this image is one that is perfect in every way, and if you have a representative of that, that is pleasing to the eye, they should then place it in front of you.
Not too high, because that will force you to look upwards, neither too low, because that would force you to look downwards, but at exactly the right height for you.
One should place the image and affix it there.
If you want to know more about the Kupar and Kunda, please visit our website.
.
Having placed the image of the Buddha in front of you, then it is useful to reflect upon the qualities of the Buddha.
Accordingly, look at the image with admiration as if it were the Tathagata's actual form and reflect thus.
Like an Udumbara flower, which appears in this world only every few hundred years, the Tathagata arises from the cause of boundless accumulation of merit and wisdom beyond imagining.
Since the Tathagata is fully adorned with the 32 excellent marks and the 80 excellent signs, seeing him is without disharmony.
In the world of gods, the extremely clear and steadfast noble rupakayas of form bodies are seen in common by all the sentient beings of that world at that time.
These forms of the awakened one, Rupakayas, also teach the Dharma there.
And they display all kinds of miracles for the benefit of those to be tamed.
They also perform various actions, including staying, departing, getting up, sleeping, and bringing immeasurable sentient beings, sources of virtue, to fruition.
Our teacher, Shakyamuni, the lion of the Shakyas, was born into the royal line of the Shakyas and eventually attained enlightenment, after which he taught the Dharma to Bodhisattvas, Sravakas, and many other gatherings of beings at Vulture's Peak and elsewhere.
While keeping in mind these qualities and attributes, think, this is what the Tathagata's form is like in shape and appearance.
The Tathagata is the embodiment of discipline, of samadhi, of supreme knowledge, complete freedom, the gathering of the wisdom and seeing of complete liberation and so on.
He is endowed with immaculate qualities that are beyond imagining.
and cannot be adequately conveyed even unto the very limits of space itself.
He closely embraces all of us with his great love.
For our sake he underwent immeasurable hardships, as you should learn from the supportive teachings for the treasury of blessings.
These tell, for instance, of how the Brahmin, Sudaraja, generated bodhicitta in such ways
that for three immeasurable aeons, practicing the six parameters, he gathered inconceivable and inexpressible accumulations of merit and wisdom, and was freed from all obscuration.
By conquering the four Maras, he completely perfected all excellent qualities without exception.
And having obtained the Kairav, the great wisdom of omniscience, he became the refuge, protector, and friend of all sentient beings until the end of time.
The virtues of recalling the unsurpassable Bhagavan, the transcendent conqueror,
paying homage to him, uttering his name, seeing his bodily form, and, closer to home, resting the mind one pointedly upon it, and so on, no matter how small, will become the cause for supreme awakening.
And accordingly then, one should reflect upon the qualities of the Buddha, thinking, since this is due to the power of the Tathagata's aspirations and inconceivable wisdom, how fortunate we are.
Hereby, generate great faith by recalling the qualities of the Buddha.
.
And so essentially, bringing to mind the Buddha to the best of one's ability.
Now, mention is made here of the major and minor marks of perfection, which are an external display of the inner qualities of omniscience.
Even if you can't bring each and every one of them to mind,
As much as you are able, try to bring those particular qualities to mind and allow them to permeate your being.
And there through, generate an appreciation for the Buddha.
Reflect upon the activities of the Buddha
as we've seen and as we can read in the discourses of the awakened one, how his very kind of sitting down, getting up, moving and so forth, brings inconceivable direct and indirect benefit to sentient beings.
So accordingly, we should reflect then upon these extraordinary activities and the benefit that they bring.
bringing them to mind will infuse the mind with faith and devotion, which will accordingly bring about a kind of natural clarity and pliancy of mind, a wholesomeness, if you will.
So we next move on to the actual focusing of our attention on this image of the Buddha.
We read,
Then, without your attention being too tightly or too loosely focused, but rather in a leisurely manner without losing mindfulness and attentiveness, focus the mind continuously on the appearance of the Tathagata's form.
.
And we read, distance in yourself from any thought other than the object of your focus.
Settle your attention only on the Buddha's form.
And so here, one should acknowledge that there may be other thoughts running through one's being.
However, at this time, one shouldn't pay them any heed.
Rather, one should make a pledge to continually place one's attention on the form of the Buddha.
And by doing so, eventually you will focus single-pointedly or one-pointedly without interruption for as long as you like.
Essentially then, practice progressively
and pass through the nine methods of mental abiding until you achieve the one-pointedness of mind of the desire realm.
And so here, mention is made then of nine methods or nine mental placements that one passes through in pursuit of the single-pointedness of mind of the desire realm.
.
then he landed in Jogpas, Sumbadi.
He landed in Jogpas.
And so then when we think of
The nine mental placements, I won't go into a great detail on them, but essentially the nine are as follows.
Resting of mind, where one rests one's attention upon the image, in this case the image of the Buddha.
And then there is continual placement or resting upon that image.
And then there is continuous resettling of the mind upon the image.
What this means is that in the early stages of practice, one will need to continually place one's mind on the image as one comes under the influence of distraction.
Nevertheless, through familiarity of replacing one's attention
the chosen image then distraction will become less and less then one will fully be able to settle one's mind that is the fourth mental placement fully settling here one is able to as the name dictates fully settle upon the image of the Buddha
Thereafter, one passes through the fifth mental placement of taming, the sixth of pacifying, the seventh of complete pacification, the eighth of one-pointedness of mind, and then the ninth where one rests in equanimity.
Essentially, with these mental placements,
one refines one's attention, one's attention that is single-pointedly focused upon the chosen image, in this case the form of the Buddha.
Today, I would like to share with you the story of my father.
When I was a child, my father was a monk.
He was a monk.
.
Now, when placing one's attention on the form of the Buddha, it can be that one is faced with difficulties in sustaining the image upon which we are focusing.
attention.
And so here are some methods that we can utilize to overcome the difficulties or the distractions that we are faced with whilst not leaving the image that we are focused upon single-pointedly.
We read
you can look at and focus upon the body in general, or in order to obtain the noble dharma and pacify dullness, focus primarily on the ushnisha, the crown protrusion on the Buddha's head, the limit of which is impossible to see.
And so here the way of focusing on these particular parts of the body is to kind of zoom in and zoom out.
Zooming in when you need to address a particular distraction and zoom out and perhaps refocusing and then zooming in on a different part of the body when
beset with a different distraction.
So accordingly, then, the first one is given, to look at the crown of the head, at the ushnisha.
Alternately, in order to obtain samadhi and pacify...
So anyway, the first one, where you look to the top of the Buddha's image, is to pacify dullness.
On the other hand, in order to obtain samadhi and pacify agitation, we are then encouraged to concentrate, or rather zoom in, on the enlightened mind's glorious knot, which is between the breasts of the Buddha, at the Buddha's heart center, as you read.
or to accomplish great merit and gain happiness you can concentrate on the appearance of the coil of hair between the Buddha's eyebrows which is as white as snow or conch and curls to the right and in order to make the great melodious sound of the Dharma pervade the whole world and to benefit sentient beings by teaching the Dharma
One should fix your mind or fix your attention on the form of the throat, the source of 60 qualities of melodious speech, the conch of the Dharma with its three lines.
So accordingly, the throat of the Buddha, there are three lines or three creases, if you like.
And accordingly, wherever it is you feel inclined to focus, concentrate your mind there unwaveringly.
.
Now when practicing calm abiding meditation or settling of mind that leads to calm abiding meditation, one will pass through five meditative experiences.
We read, when focusing your mind like this, at the very beginning it is like catching a snake.
The mind is so wild and untamed that the first stage of meditation is called the experience
of movement like a waterfall.
It's important here to reflect on the experience of some when practicing calm abiding meditation.
It can be that we feel that I'm getting worse and worse.
Mind is getting more and more agitated.
There's more and more kind of discursive thought passing through.
But I don't think this is the case.
What usually happens
is we don't really look within.
We're so focused on the objects that are proffered to us through the sense doors, we do not take adequate time to look within.
And when we do, rather than kind of the finding that the mind is as peaceful as we'd like to believe it actually is, when that calmness and clarity comes through taking the time to allow ourselves the opportunity to look within,
what we find is agitation and an incredible amount of thought that's always been there, it's just that we're noticing it for the first time.
.
As we read, at this stage you have the impression that your mind is in constant motion from the sutra requested by Subahu.
This mind is like lightning, wind and clouds, like the waves of a giant ocean, cunning, indulging in everything it desires, moving, straying.
Reflect.
I must certainly tame it.
Accordingly, one should reflect, since all sentient beings have fallen under the sway of this completely distracted mind, I will persevere without giving into laziness, come what may.
For if one perseveres, there is nothing one cannot accomplish.
Accordingly, endeavor to maintain the focus for as long as you can.
And, by persevering in this way, discursive thoughts, which were so apparent and rough, wild and turbulent, will settle down slightly after a while.
But there will still be the busyness of the many different thoughts, a bubbling stream of restless mental activity.
This recognition is the second meditation experience of attainment, and it is likened to a river flowing through a narrow canyon.
.
The second example of a river flowing through a narrow canyon is used because although a river running through said canyon is still very turbulent and noisy, it is a little slower than a waterfall.
If you keep persevering and continue the practice, then you will feel that inwardly the mind's thoughts are slowing down and you are able to remain with the object of focus.
However,
If you carefully examine, you will see that you are still involved in a continuous stream of many subtle conceptual thoughts or discursive thoughts.
At this point, you've reached the third experience called the experience of familiarization, and it is likened to a gently flowing stream.
.
When you look at a stream from afar, it seems to be still, and you cannot tell that it is moving.
But when you get up close, you'll see that it is moving, alight and rippling.
Accordingly then, from this point on, if you don't stop persevering, but keep on striving, you will have less hardship and suffering than before.
So exert yourself continuously, we are told.
By practicing like this, even the movement of subtle conceptual thoughts will be pacified.
And as long as you have the conditioning for the focus, you will be able to remain as long as you like.
Yet this does not mean that you are completely impervious to circumstances.
And this then is the fourth meditation experience called the experience of stability, which is like an ocean free from waves, since the mind abides and is stable.
.
Having reached this far, then without having to undergo great hardships, the fifth meditation experience, perfection, which is likened to a mountain, will arise as long as you continue to familiarize yourself with the state over time.
And this then is synonymous with effortless engagement.
The mind naturally mixes with whatever you focus on, and without the need for any effort, remains steadily wherever you want it to.
Conceptual or discursive thoughts no longer have the power to shake your mind.
And this is the accomplishment, is what is called the one-pointedness of a mind of the desire realm.
Thank you.
And so when we reflect upon the result, which is the one-pointedness or single-pointedness of a mind of the desire realm.
So this is the result of a way of training in Khayamavadi meditation, which is levied out according to five experiences of meditation.
And so you will recall, I went through earlier the nine mental placements, the result is the same.
So these are just different ways of delineation.
.
At this time, various experiences resulting from the mind's abiding will also arise.
When you have become familiar with this state, mind and body are said to become supple.
As body and mind become workable in this way, whatever objects of focus you settle the mind upon, even if you remain for several days, there is no sense at all of either the body or the mind being unable to cope.
The body feels as light as cotton and the mind is pervaded by the bliss of vivid clarity.
this subtleness is rough and heavy at first and has a sense of solidity but with familiarity the heaviness fades and there arises an unwavering some shamatha that is extremely fine and clear like a shadow
a mind of meditative concentration that is in accord with the main part of the practice.
This kind of meditation has the name shamatha, calm abiding, since it is a mind endowed with subtleness.
.
this mind also corresponds to the aspect of the first meditative absorptions capable preparatory stage
There is nothing that this kind of meditative concentration is incapable of, be it meditation with a conceptual focus or meditation without concepts, as in the meditations on emptiness and the like.
There are several ways of counting the stages of accomplishing shamatha.
such as the four mental engagements or the six powers.
But essentially, they are all included in the following.
The mind remains totally concentrated with mindfulness and attentiveness for as long as possible on whichever objects you choose to focus.
And as you familiarize yourself with this, the five meditative experiences will arrive.
.
Accordingly, when you have accomplished shamatha, karma-abiding meditation in this way, the strength of the mind's workability, pliancy if you will, gives the body a gleaming complexion and makes it comfortable and strong.
The mind too becomes clear and lucid.
and settles on any object of your choice.
Body and mind are saturated with immeasurable joy and bliss.
The afflictions are reduced and you'll have an experience concordant with the extraordinary joy of inner solitude.
By the strength of the merit of practicing this way, with the focus on the form of the Buddha and through the Buddha's blessing, you'll come to see the Buddha, either in actuality or in dreams, receiving the Dharma and all sorts of excellent qualities will arise.
And so accordingly, focusing on the form of the Buddha and through the Buddha's blessing, you, the meditator, will ultimately come to see the Buddha either in actuality or in dreams.
And thereby, you will receive Dharma teachings and so on.
And all sorts of wondrous, excellent qualities of various sorts will arise within you.
And so accordingly then, I've given you the teaching, a brief teaching on the method of calm abiding.
And so you see, by this, practicing in this way, you'll notice, the text reads, when you have accomplished shamatha in this way, the strength of the mind's workability gives the body a gleaming complexion.
And so you can save on makeup.
If you look around here at the faces of all of our teachers, you can see in the radiance of their faces, the kind of natural radiance in their faces is reflective of the inner qualities of realization and experience.